Martha Graham Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Martha Graham Collection 1896-2003 (bulk 1926-1991)
ML31.G727
Graham, Martha
350,100 items 398 containers 590 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Martha Graham was an American modern dancer, choreographer, teacher and company director. The Martha Graham Collection is comprised of materials that document her career and trace the history of the development of her company, Martha Graham Dance Company, which became the Martha Graham Center of Contemporary Dance, and school, Martha Graham School, later to be called the Martha Graham School of Contemporary Dance.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Barber, Samuel, 1910-1981.; Copland, Aaron, 1900-1990.; Dello Joio, Norman, 1913-2008.; El-Dabh, Halim, 1921-; Emmons, Beverly.; Graham, Martha--Archives.; Graham, Martha--Correspondence.; Graham, Martha--Photographs.; Graham, Martha.; Graham, Martha.; Hindemith, Paul, 1895-1963.; Horst, Louis.; Hovhaness, Alan, 1911-2000.; Karan, Donna, 1948-; Lester, Eugene.; Menotti, Gian Carlo, 1911-2007.; Noguchi, Isamu, 1904-1988.; Noguchi, Isamu, 1904-1988.; Riegger, Wallingford, 1885-1961.; Rosenthal, Jean, 1912-; Rosenthal, Jean, 1912-; Schuman, William, 1910-1992.; Skelton, Thomas R.; Starer, Robert.; Ter-Arutunian, Rouben, 1920-; Tipton, Jennifer.; Weissberger, L. Arnold, 1907-1981.
Organizations
Graham (Martha) Collection (Library of Congress); Martha Graham Center of Contemporary Dance.; Martha Graham Center of Contemporary Dance.; Martha Graham Dance Company.; Martha Graham Dance Company.; Martha Graham School of Contemporary Dance.; Martha Graham School of Contemporary Dance.
Subjects
Choreographers--United States--Correspondence.; Choreographers--United States--Photographs.; Choreographers--United States.; Choreography--United States.; Costume design--United States.; Dance companies--United States.; Dance schools--United States.; Dance--Production and direction.; Dance--Stage-setting and scenery--United States.; Dance--United States.; Dancers--Photographs.; Dancers--United States.; Modern dance music.; Modern dance--United States.
Form/Genre
Artifacts (Object genre); Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Photographic prints.; Programs (Documents); Scrapbooks.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Purchased with funds from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation in 1998.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
The moving image materials were transferred to the Library of Congress, Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division where they are identified as part of the Graham (Martha) Collection (Library of Congress).
Related Material
The Library of Congress is rich in materials that illuminate the career of Martha Graham and, in addition to the Martha Graham Collection, other Graham-related resources in the Music Division include the
Aaron Copland Collection
, the Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge Collection, Herta Moselsio Collection, Martha Graham Legacy Archive, Nathan Kroll Collection, Helen McGehee and Umaña Collection of Dance Materials, Miriam Cole Collection, Benjamin Garber Collection, and Erick Hawkins Collection. There is valuable correspondence between Graham and former chief of the Music Division, Harold Spivack, in the Music Division’s Old Correspondence File. Because the Music Division holds the archival collections of many of the people who composed for Graham, the researcher is urged to consult one of the division’s music specialists for additional suggestions. The Manuscript Division holds the
Lucy Kroll Papers
(Graham’s agent) and the
Muriel Rukeyser Papers
, which contain the correspondence of Frances G. Wickes, Graham’s psychiatrist. In addition, the holdings of the Prints and Photographs Division include images of Martha Graham.
Access and Restrictions
The Martha Graham Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Martha Graham, a pioneer in the establishment of American modern dance, was one of the principal choreographers of the twentieth century. Her work, which spanned more than seven decades, resulted in the development of a movement technique and a body of 180 choreographic works. Known also for her innovative collaborations, Graham worked with sculptor Isamu Noguchi, who created over thirty-five designs for Graham works; lighting designer Jean Rosenthal; costume designer Halston; and many composers, including Aaron Copland, Samuel Barber, Robert Starer, William Schuman, and Louis Horst, who acted as accompanist, composer, and music director for Graham from 1926 to 1948. Graham founded a dance company in the 1920s that continues to perform her repertory (www.marthagraham.org).
The following timeline makes reference to only a few of Graham’s choreographic works. For a complete repertory list, please consult Don McDonagh’s book, Martha Graham (1973).
Date Event
1894 May 11 Martha Graham is born in Allegheny, Pennsylvania
1916 Graham begins studies with Ted Shawn and Ruth St. Denis at their Denishawn School
1918 Graham begins teaching at the Denishawn School
1919 Graham dances with Denishawn until 1923, appearing in title roles such as Xochitl
1923-1925 Graham appears in John Murray Anderson’s Greenwich Village Follies, dancing Ted Shawn’s Serenata Morisca and Michio Ito’s The Garden of Kama
1925 Graham establishes her first dance company and begins to develop her specialized dance technique
1926 Graham presents her first independent concert at the 48th Street Theater in New York City, assisted by the Martha Graham Concert Group. The New York Herald Tribune noted, “Miss Graham gave a successful performance, showing ability to present a mood or a picture, with the assets of grace, agility, effective poses and well chosen costumes”
1927 In a review of a program at New York City’s Little Theatre, the New York American said “Slender, sinuous and supple, and ever with a definite command of grace, Miss Graham may have many competitors in Terpsichore’s guild, but few rivals”
1928 Graham begins an association with the Neighborhood Playhouse and, in conjunction with the Cleveland Orchestra, Graham performs in Nuages and Fetes (music by Debussy) with dancer/choreographer Michio Ito
1929 Graham presents a concert which includes her first group masterpiece, Heretic
1930 Graham begins a seven-year relationship with Washington Irving High School in New York City and presents yearly concerts. She performs in Léonide Massine’s Rite of Spring with the Philadelphia Orchestra
1932 Graham is the first dancer to receive a John Simon Guggenheim Foundation Fellowship
1936 Graham tours the United States in a solo program. She is invited, but rejects, an offer to represent the U.S. at the International Dance Festival, held in conjunction with the Berlin Olympics. She states: “so many artists have been persecuted that I refuse to identify myself with the regime that made it possible”
1937 At the invitation of President and Mrs. Roosevelt, Graham is the first dancer to appear at the White House. Graham and her company make their first transcontinental tour
1938 Graham begins a relationship with Bennington Collect in Vermont where she teaches each summer until 1941. Erick Hawkins becomes the first man to join her dance company. Merce Cunningham joins in 1939
1944 Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge commissions three works: Imagined Wing (music by Darius Milhaud), Hérodiade (music by Paul Hindemith), and Appalachian Spring (music by Aaron Copland). The works are premiered in the Library of Congress Coolidge Auditorium. Writing about Appalachian Spring for the New York Times, critic John Martin states, “nothing Miss Graham has done before has had such deep joyousness about it”
1948 Graham marries dancer/choreographer Erick Hawkins
1950 The Louisville Symphony Orchestra commissions Graham to choreograph a new work (Judith to music by William Schuman). The Columbus [Ohio] Dispatch declares the work to be “a dance of smashing impact”
1951 Graham’s second commission by the Louisville Symphony Orchestra results in The Triumph of St. Joan (music by Norman Dello Joio)
1954 The Graham company tours Europe, sponsored by the U.S. State Department.
1955 The Graham company tours Asia, sponsored by the U.S. State Department
1957 Graham receives a Dance Magazine Award
1960 Graham is recipient of a Capezio Award
1965 Graham receives an Aspen Award in Humanities
1966 Graham receives honorary doctorate from Harvard
1968 Graham choreographs the last new dance in which she appears (The Lady of the House of Sleep with music by Robert Starer). The Washington Post reports that it is “one of the most tangled and troubled of Graham dances”
1969 At age 64, Graham dances for the last time on 20 April and retires from the stage
1971 Graham receives honorary doctorates from Yale and Wesleyan
1976 President Gerald Ford presents the Medal of Freedom to Graham
1978 Graham choreographs Frescoes (music by Samuel Barber) for the dedication ceremonies of the Metropolitan Museum of Art’s Sackler Wing
1979 Graham receives a Kennedy Center Honors Award, Washington, DC and the Royal Medal of Jordan
1981 Graham receives the Samuel H. Scripps American Dance Festival Award
1982 Graham accepts the Algur H. Meadows Award for Excellence in the Arts, from Southern Methodist University
1984 The Chevalier de la Légion d’Honneur is presented to Graham by President François Mitterand
1985 Graham receives a National Medal of Arts awarded by President Ronald Reagan and the Carina Ari Medal, which is presented by Princess Christina of Sweden
1991 April 1 Martha Graham dies in New York City
Scope and Content Note
The Martha Graham Collection is comprised of materials that document the career of modern dance pioneer Martha Graham and trace the history of the development of her company, the Martha Graham Dance Company, which became the Martha Graham Center of Contemporary Dance, and school, Martha Graham School, later to be called the Martha Graham School of Contemporary Dance. The collection also includes, unprocessed and unavailable for viewing at this time, five linear feet of materials from the Martha Graham School of Contemporary Dance and four linear feet of archival materials relating to Graham’s sister, Georgia Graham Sargent.
Organization of the Martha Graham Collection
The Martha Graham Collection is organized into fifteen series:
Music Inventory
Scrapbooks
Photographic Material
Clippings
Public Relations, Fundraising, and Special Events
New York City Seasons and National and International Tours, 1948-1996
Choreographic Notebooks
Correspondence
Production Elements
Special Projects
Writings by and about Martha Graham
Programs
Business Papers
Personal Papers and Finances
Realia
http://lccn.loc.gov/2010561026
Container List
- Music Inventory (Box 1-118; 122; 124-197)
  One of the highlights of the collection is the Music Inventory that describes seventy-three of Graham’s works. It consists of original holograph or autograph scores by composers such as Aaron Copland, Samuel Barber, Alan Hovhaness, Louis Horst, Halim El-Dabh, Eugene Lester, Norman Dello Joio, Paul Hindemith, Gian-Carlo Menotti, Robert Starer, William Schuman, and Wallingford Riegger. The series also includes orchestral parts and piano rehearsal scores which often include choreographic notes.
  Arranged by title of choreographic work, however, composers and alternate or original titles of compositions are cross-referenced in the finding aid.
  - Choreographed Works (Box 1-191, 193-194)
    - Acrobats of God (1960) Composer: Carlos Surinach
      - Violoncello part (Box-folder 193/1)
    - Acts of Light (1981) Composer: Carl Nielson, Nielsen’s titles: Pan og Syrinx [Pan and Syrinx], op. 49; Ved en Ung kunstners baare [At the Bier of a Young Artist]; Helios, op. 17.
      - Photocopy published full score (Box-folder 1/1)
      - Photocopy published full score (Box-folder 1/2)
      - Published extra parts (Box-folder 1/3-6)
      - Published extra parts (Box-folder 1/7-9)
      - Extra parts (Box-folder 2/1)
      - Photocopy full score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 2/2)
      - Full score with choreographic notes, part II (Ved en ung Kunstners Baare), (2 copies) (Box-folder 2/3)
      - Published parts, part II (Box-folder 2/4)
      - Extra parts, part II (Box-folder 2/5)
      - Photocopy full score, with choreographic notes, part III (Helios) (Box-folder 2/6)
      - Photocopy full score, with choreographic notes, part III (Helios) (Box-folder 2/7)
      - Published parts (Box-folder 2/8-10)
      - Extra parts, part III (Box-folder 3/1-4)
    - Alcestis (1960) Composer: Vivian Fine
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 4/1)
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 4/2)
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 5/1)
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 5/2)
      - Piano rehearsal score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 5/3)
      - Piano rehearsal score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 5/4)
      - Ozalid parts (Box-folder 6/1-2)
      - Extra parts (Box-folder 6/3-4)
    - American Document (1938) Composer: Ray Green, Set to music by John Corigliano in 1989.
      - Photocopy full score: Concerto for Oboe and Orchestra (1989 version) (Box-folder 7/1)
      - Ink piano rehearsal score, with choreographic notes; music by Ray Green and Louis Horst (Box-folder 8/1)
      - Ink piano rehearsal score (Box-folder 8/2)
      - Photocopy of piano score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 8/3)
      - Photocopy of piano score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 8/4)
      - Photocopy of piano score (incomplete) (Box-folder 8/5)
      - Negative Photostat of piano score (Box-folder 8/6)
      - Ink parts (Box-folder 8/7)
    - Adromache’s Lament (1982) Composer: Samuel Barber, Barber’s title: Andromache’s Farewell.
      - Piano/vocal score (Box-folder 9/1)
      - Wind parts (Box-folder 9/2)
      - Percussion-harp parts (Box-folder 9/3)
      - String parts (Box-folder 9/4)
      - Extra string parts (Box-folder 9/5)
    - Appalachian Spring (1944) Composer: Aaron Copland, Copland’s title: Ballet for Martha.
      - Copyist’s original parts, woodwinds-piano (Box-folder 10/1)
      - Copyist’s string parts Ozalid full score with pencil annotations Ozalid rehearsal piano score with choreographic notes (copy 1 missing) Ozalid piano score, with choreographic notes (copy 2) (Box-folder 10/2)
      - Ozalid copyist’s set of parts (Box-folder 11/1-3)
      - Ozalid extra parts (Box-folder 12/1-3)
      - New parts, string (Box-folder 13/1-2)
      - Extra string parts (Box-folder 14/1)
      - Parts (flute, clarinet, bassoon, piano) (Box-folder 14/2)
    - Archaic Hours, The (1969) Composer: Eugene Lester
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 15/1)
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 15/2)
      - Ozalid piano rehearsal score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 15/3)
      - Ozalid piano rehearsal score, no choreographic notes (Box-folder 15/4)
      - Ozalid piano rehearsal score, with choreographic notes, incomplete (Box-folder 15/5)
      - Copyist’s deschens parts (Box-folder 16/1)
      - Extra parts (Box-folder 16/2)
      - Extra parts (Box-folder 17/1-3)
      - Extra parts (Box-folder 18/1-3)
    - Ardent Song (1954) Composer: Alan Hovhaness, Hovhaness’s title: Music for Martha Graham.
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 19/1)
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 19/2)
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 19/3)
      - Copyist’s parts (Box-folder 20/1-2)
      - Extra parts (Box-folder 20/3)
    - Arma, Paul [Imre Weisshaus] see Satyric Festival Song
    - Baal Shem (1926) Composer: Ernst Bloch
      - Piano/Violin part (Box-folder 193/2)
    - Baccanale (1931) Composer: Wallingford Reigger, Baccanale no. 2 choreographed in 1932, also to music by Reigger.
      - Piano four hands (Box-folder 193/3)
      - Photocopy, with notes (Box-folder 193/4)
      - Photocopy, piano four hands (Box-folder 193/5)
      - Ink copyists’ parts of oboe, piccolo, and piano (Box-folder 193/6)
    - Ballet for Martha see Appalachian Spring
    - Barber, Samuel see Andromache’s Lament see Cave of the Heart
    - Bloch, Ernst see Baal Shem
    - But Not For Me (1999) Composer: George Gershwin, Choreography by Susan Stroman.
      - Photocopy of full score (Box-folder 21)
    - Canticle for Innocent Comedians (1952) Composer: Thomas Ribbink
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 22/1)
      - Photocopy full score (Box-folder 22/2)
      - Ink and pencil piano score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 23/1)
      - Photocopy piano score, with pencil notes (Box-folder 24/1)
      - Photocopy piano score (Box-folder 24/2)
      - Photocopy piano score (copy 3) (Box-folder 24/3)
      - Ink piano score, with corrections (incomplete) (Box-folder 24/4)
      - Deschen piano score (Box-folder 24/5)
      - Deschen parts (Box-folder 25/1)
      - Deschen parts (string) (Box-folder 25/2)
      - Obsolete parts (Box-folder 25/3)
      - Deschen parts; ink parts (flute, clarinet, oboe bassoon, horn, percussion) (Box-folder 25/4)
      - Photocopy percussion (2 copies) (Box-folder 25/5)
      - Ink vocal score (Box-folder 26/1)
      - Photocopy vocal score (Box-folder 26/2)
      - Photocopy vocal score (Box-folder 26/3)
      - Ink string parts (Box-folder 26/4)
      - Extra parts (Box-folder 26/5)
      - Deschen parts (Box-folder 193/7)
      - Photocopy vocal score (Box-folder 193/8)
    - Cave of the Heart (1946) Composer: Samuel Barber, Barber’s title: Medea.; Graham’s title for first performance: Serpent Heart.
      - Ink rehearsal piano score with choreographic notes (Box-folder 27/1)
      - Ozalid piano score (Box-folder 27/2)
      - Ozalid wind parts (Box-folder 27/3)
      - Ozalid piano part (Box-folder 27/4)
      - Ozalid string parts (Box-folder 27/5)
      - Ozalid extra parts (Box-folder 27/6)
      - Extra parts (Box-folder 28/1-4)
    - Celebration (1934) Composer: Louis Horst, Reconstruction 1987.
      - Rehearsal piano score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 29/1)
      - Photocopy rehearsal piano score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 29/2)
      - Photocopy rehearsal piano score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 29/3)
      - Ozalid parts (Box-folder 29/4)
      - Extra parts (Box-folder 29/5)
      - Copyist’s deschens (Box-folder 29/6)
    - Chávez, Carlos see Dark Meadow
    - Chronicle see Prelude to Action; Steps in the Street
    - Circe (1963) Composer: Alan Hovhaness, Hovhaness’s title: Circe, op. 204.
      - Ozalid full score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 30/1)
      - Ozalid full score, revised (Box-folder 30/2)
      - Holograph piano rehearsal score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 30/3)
      - Photostats (negative and positive), piano rehearsal score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 30/4)
      - Piano score in pencil, reduction by Howard Douenfeld (Box-folder 30/5)
      - Photocopy of piano score, reduction by Howard Douenfeld (Box-folder 30/6)
      - Piano score in pencil, fragment and negative Photostat (Box-folder 30/7)
      - Ozalid parts, winds (Box-folder 30/8)
      - Ozalid parts, percussion-harp (Box-folder 30/9)
      - Ozalid parts, strings (Box-folder 30/10)
      - Extra parts (Box-folder 31/1-4)
    - Circe, op. 204 see Circe
    - Clytemnestra (1958) Composer: Halim El-Dabh
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 32/1)
      - Ozalid full score, act 1, part 1 (Box-folder 32/2)
      - Ozalid full score, act 1, part 2 (Box-folder 32/3)
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 33/1)
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 33/2)
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 33/3)
      - Photocopy piano score, with cuts in pencil (Box-folder 34/1)
      - Piano score of “Prologue,” with choreographic notes (Box-folder 34/2)
      - Ozalid piano score of act 1, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 34/3)
      - Ozalid piano score of act 2 and epilogue, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 34/4)
      - Photocopy piano score (complete) (Box-folder 35/1)
      - Piano score of “Prologue,” with choreographic notes (Box-folder 35/2)
      - Piano score of act 1, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 35/3)
      - Piano score of act 2 and epilogue, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 35/4)
      - Ozalid flute (piccolo) part (Box-folder 36/1)
      - Ozalid oboe/English horn part (Box-folder 36/2)
      - Ozalid clarinet part (Box-folder 36/3)
      - Ozalid bassoon part (Box-folder 36/4)
      - Ozalid horn part (Box-folder 37/1)
      - Ozalid trumpet part (Box-folder 37/2)
      - Ozalid trombone part (Box-folder 37/3)
      - Ozalid percussion part (Box-folder 37/4)
      - Ozalid piano part (Box-folder 37/5)
      - Ozalid harp part (Box-folder 37/6)
      - Ozalid violin I part (Box-folder 38/1)
      - Ozalid violin II part (Box-folder 38/2)
      - Ozalid viola part (Box-folder 38/3)
      - Ozalid violoncello part (Box-folder 38/4)
      - Ozalid double bass part (Box-folder 38/5)
    - Concerto a tre see Secular Games
    - Concertante see Part Real-Part Dream
    - Copland, Aaron see Appalachian Spring; Dithyrambic
    - Corigliano, John see American Document
    - Cortege of Eagles (1967) Composer: Eugene Lester, Lester’s title: Hecabe.
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 47/1)
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 47/2)
      - Photocopy full score (Hecabe) (Box-folder 47/3)
      - Photocopy full score (Hecabe) (Box-folder 47/4)
      - Ozalid piano score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 47/5)
      - Ozalid piano score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 47/6)
      - Ozalid parts (Box-folder 45/1-3)
      - Extra parts (Box-folder 45/4)
      - Unfoldered box of piano mutes (Box 46)
      - Extra parts (Box-folder 46/1-4)
      - Misc. parts (Box-folder 46/5)
    - Crumb, George see Phaedra’s Dream
    - Dance Songs see Satyric Festival Song
    - Dances of the Golden Hall (1982) Composer: Andrzej Panufnik, Panufnik’s title: Nocturne for Orchestra.
      - Published full score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 48/1)
      - Published full score, without choreographic notes (Box-folder 48/2)
      - Ozalid parts (Box-folder 48/3-6)
      - Ozalid extra parts (Box-folder 48/7-9)
    - Dark Meadow (1946) Composer: Carlos Chávez, Chávez’s title: La hija de Cólquidea.
      - Ink conductor’s score (Box-folder 49/1)
      - Ink piano rehearsal score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 49/2)
      - Ozalid parts (Box-folder 50/1-2)
      - Extra parts (Box-folder 50/3-6)
      - Copyist’s deschens of bassoon part (Box-folder 50/7)
    - Deaths and Entrances (1943) Composer: Hunter Johnson
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 52/1)
      - Ozalid full score (Box-folder 52/2)
      - Ozalid full score, chamber version (Box-folder 51/1)
      - Photocopy/ink piano rehearsal score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 51/2)
      - Photocopy piano rehearsal score, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 51/3)
      - Photocopy piano rehearsal score, with choreographic notes, (fragment) (Box-folder 51/4)
      - Ozalid full score, reduced version, with choreographic notes (Box-folder 51/5)
      - Copyist’s parts (ink), chamber version (Box-folder 53/1-2)
      - Parts (old set) (Box-folder 53/3-5)
      - Parts (old set) (Box-folder 54/1-4)
      - Parts (new set) (Box-folder 55/1-3)
      - Extra parts (new set) (Box-folder 56/1-2)
      - Extra parts (new set) (Box-folder 57/1-2)